THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、組織名均為虛構）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（與任何特定事件或現象無關）
In that case, will you put makeup on me?
那麼，你能幫我化妝嗎？
What?
什麼？
He doesn't need it.
沒有必要吧
Throughout history, there have been many pointless battles.
歷史上發生過許多次無意義的戰爭
Some of them were caused by ruinous beauties.
其中不乏因為傾國美女而引起的
If someone as beautiful as a heavenly maiden put on makeup…
本就已經美如天仙的大人 要是再化上妝的話…
-Are you trying to end a nation? -Why?
-您是想滅國嗎？ -為什麼是這種結論？
What are you thinking about?
真是，到底想像了些什麼啊？
How do you create your face powder?
你臉上的粉膏是怎麼弄的？
Oh, the makeup to make yourself look dull, not beautiful.
原來不是要變得更美 而是想變得平凡一點啊
I dry some clay and turn it into powder,
這是將黏土曬乾搗成粉
and mix it with oil.
再和油混合而成
Can you prepare that in a short time?
這個能馬上做出來嗎？
Yes. I only need one night.
可以，只需一晚即可
It's a bit too dark for you, Sir Jinshi.
這對壬氏大人來說，稍微太深了點呢
If only there were some medicine to change my face.
要是有能改變容貌的藥，就方便多了
You could paint some lacquer on your face,
只要把漆往臉上刷就夠了
but it would stay that way forever.
但一輩子都恢復不了原貌就是
Figures.
我想也是
If your goal is to look like a commoner,
如果只是想扮成平民的話
I could do that for you.
也不是辦不到
Please do that then.
那麼就有勞你了
Make me look like a completely different person.
把我變成跟現在完全不同的模樣吧
What is he planning?
不曉得他到底想做什麼
In that case…
但是
I'll go all in!
要做就要做得徹底
So cold!
好冷
Good morning…
早安…
What's wrong? Already in a bad mood? It's still morning.
怎麼了？一早就不開心的樣子
No, you'll be beautiful all day as usual.
沒事，壬氏大人今天也十分美麗呢
Are you making fun of me?
這是新的挖苦方式嗎？
Sir Jinshi, so you really want to become another person?
壬氏大人是真心想換個模樣嗎？
I've been saying that since last night.
我昨晚不就這麼說了？
Then, excuse me.
那麼，請恕我失禮
Oh, wow!
哎呀
What is it?
怎麼突然湊過來？
No commoner would burn such expensive incense.
沒有庶民會焚燒如此高級的薰香
Your clothes right now are daily wear for a low-class government official.
現在您所穿的 最多也不過是下級官吏的便衣
It has no business being near high-quality fragrant wood from overseas.
應該無緣接觸這種 海外訂購的最高級香木才是
You can tell?
真虧你分得出來
I just developed a sense of smell
因為要分辨藥草和毒草
to differentiate medicinal herbs and poison.
所以我的鼻子很靈敏
Do you know how we recognize rich clients in brothels?
大人曉得青樓如何分辨貴客嗎？
No. Is it by figure or clothes?
不曉得，看體型或衣服嗎？
That too, but we use one more thing: Smell.
那也是一種方法 不過還有一招，就是氣味
A customer smelling of many different scents in bad taste
散發出好幾種品味低俗香味的客人
is rich, but is at a high risk of having STIs.
雖然有錢，但也很可能染有性病
If they smell like livestock, they don't bathe and are unsanitary.
若是帶有家畜臭味 就是沒洗澡而不衛生
Most new customers that come to visit Verdigris House are turned away.
造訪綠青館的生客，通常都會被趕走
With these things, you should ask those who know about the world.
那種事情 去問熟知那個世界的人會更快喔
Sir Gaoshun, could you prepare new clothes for him?
高順大人 能麻煩您準備替換的衣服嗎？
Preferably, something that hasn't been washed, and smells a bit.
可以的話，最好是留有一些臭味 還沒有洗過的髒衣服
Oh, my.
天啊
-Understood. -Hey!
-明白了 -喂
While we're waiting for that…
那麼，在這段時間…
-What is that? -Oil and salt.
-這是？ -油和鹽
We'll take away the luster in his hair, and worsen his hair texture.
這可以消去頭髮的光澤，讓質地變差
Excuse me, sir.
失禮了
This is probably enough.
這樣差不多了
Hey, you don't have to tie it with scrap fabric.
哎呀，再怎麼說 也不用這種破布束髮吧？
Commoners tie their hair with whatever's lying around.
平民只要能束髮，用什麼都行
Are you sure this is good?
真的要穿這個嗎？
He could smell a little worse.
再臭一點也行的
Sir Jinshi, please take off your clothes.
壬氏大人，請您褪下衣服吧
Oh, sure…
喔…
He looks like a heavenly maiden,
雖說是像仙女一樣的大人
but he has well-proportioned muscles.
卻有肌肉勻稱的身材呢
May I use that towel?
可以借用那裡的手巾嗎？
You can, but what will you use it for?
可以是可以，你要做什麼？
I'm changing his body.
我要改變他的體型
Can you both please help me?
不好意思，能麻煩兩位也來幫忙嗎？
Sir Gaoshun, hold this.
高順大人按著那邊
-Okay. -Ms. Suiren, please hold here.
-好的 -水蓮大人按住這裡
-Got it! -Put clothes on the top, and now…
-知道了 -然後再穿上衣服的話…
Oh, my.
天啊
It's odd to see Sir Jinshi's face on such a clumsy figure.
如此臃腫的體型搭上壬氏大人的臉 感覺真是奇妙
Now, let's do the face.
接下來是臉
I created some face powders with dark colors.
我準備了多種深色的粉膏
I'll use this to create sunburnt skin, just like a commoner.
這樣就能做出 像是平民飽受日曬的膚色
Close your eyes, please.
請把眼睛閉上
All right.
好
His face is beautiful even from close up.
就算湊近摸，也是過份地細緻
He has no facial hair or visible pores.
別說是汗毛了，連毛孔都沒看見
What would female makeup look like on him?
要是化女妝，會是多麼…
Here it is! Makeup that Big Sis Meimei forced on me.
有了，是梅梅姐姐強塞給我的東西
Hey, are we done yet?
我說，還沒好嗎？
Can you close your mouth too? Not too tight.
能請您也把嘴巴閉上嗎？別太用力
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
I'm glad it was just us three.
還好這裡只有我們三人
If anyone else were here, it would've caused an uproar.
要是還有別人，一定會出大事的
Hey, what's going on?
喂，怎麼了？
It's nothing, sir.
不，什麼事都沒有
That hurts. What happened?
很痛耶，到底怎麼了？
-Nothing. -It was nothing.
-沒怎麼樣 -沒有怎麼樣
Yes, nothing at all.
對，沒怎麼樣喔
Let's get back on track.
重新繼續吧
I'll apply face powder in a patchy way,
用粉膏在臉上加上斑點
and create eye bags with a dark color.
然後畫上黑眼圈
Add some moles,
加上一些痣
and draw eyebrows asymmetrically.
然後改變左右眉毛的粗細
I'll use leftover face powder
將剩下的粉膏
to create pigmentation spots around the body.
塗抹在身體各處做出塊斑
Add some powder under the nails to create unsanitary hands.
指甲間也塞入粉膏 弄出骯髒的雙手模樣
Those are strong, male hands. Not elegant hands like I imagined.
是雙健壯男人的手 果然不可能是纖纖玉手嗎？
He has blisters.
手上有長繭
I thought he only held brushes and chopsticks.
我以為他平常只會拿毛筆和筷子
Does he fight with swords or sticks?
他也有在練劍術或棍術嗎？
Those skills are not needed for eunuchs.
宦官應該不需要這些本事的
I don't need to ask pointless questions.
算了，沒必要問這種無聊的問題
Wow, they look dirty.
喔，看起來很髒呢
-Here you are. -Is that a drink?
-請用 -是喝的嗎？
Oh! What is this?
這是什麼？
Please lick it slowly
請先用這個沾濕嘴唇
as if wetting your lips, and swallow.
慢慢舔舐然後吞下
Your lips and throat will swell, and your voice will change.
這樣嘴唇和喉嚨就會發腫 您的聲音也會改變
What's in it?
裡頭裝了什麼？
Different types of stimulants.
裝了數種刺激性物質
They're very spicy, but not poisonous, so don't worry.
雖然很辣，但並沒有毒，請放心
Please drink it all.
請全部喝下
Some finishing touches.
最後一步
It's cotton.
這是棉花
Please stuff these in your cheeks to change your face shape.
為了改變臉型，請把這些含在臉頰下
We're all finished.
完成了
Is it really you, Young Master?
這真的是少爺嗎？
Don't call me Young Master.
別叫我少爺了
He still looks pretty handsome.
即便如此，看起來仍然有三分俊俏
Can't do anything with his natural beauty.
天生麗質還真是困擾啊
I've done all I can.
不過，我已經把能做的都做了
Now, I can visit home for the first time in a while!
那麼，我也久違地可以回家了
Xiaomao, you said you were visiting home today, right?
小貓，你說過今天要回老家，對吧？
Yes. I got some time off until tomorrow…
對，我休息到明日為止
I haven't seen him make this face before…
高順大人露出了少見的表情
In that case, Sir Jinshi will be taking the same route part of the way.
那麼，你半路上會和壬氏大人同行呢
If he's disguised, it would be strange if he is accompanied by
既然已經喬裝易容了 若是還帶著平常的隨從
his usual servants.
會啟人疑竇的吧？
Oh, that's true.
哎呀，說得有道理呢
Don't you think so too, Sir Jinshi?
壬氏大人也這麼覺得吧？
That's true.
的確
It would help me a lot if you were with me.
你要是能來，就幫上大忙了
Oh, no! Sir Jinshi likes the idea too!
不好，壬氏大人上鉤了！
I'm sorry, Sir Jinshi, but if I were to accompany you, it would look
十分抱歉，但要是 我在壬氏大人身邊的話
very plain.
恐怕也沒有太大幫助吧
Of course, a homely servant may be better for a homely master,
雖說穿著土氣的主人 或許適合搭配土氣的隨從
but people do know me as your live-in maid, so…
但大家都知道 我是您的貼身侍女，若是…
That's not true.
沒那回事
In that case, you should disguise yourself too.
那樣的話 小貓也喬裝一下不就行了？
-What? -That's a great idea.
-什麼？ -這主意不錯
I have it all!
各種用具也都有喔
But…
但是…
You just have to look very unlike your usual self, right?
只要不像平常的樣貌就行了，對吧？
Right?
對吧？
Yes…
好…
I only have bad feelings about this.
只有不好的預感啊
Sir Jinshi, your posture is too perfect.
壬氏大人，您的姿勢太優雅了
You watch what you're saying too.
你才是，別再這麼畢恭畢敬的
If you say my name, my disguise is pointless.
再說你喊我名字 喬裝不就沒意義了？
In that case, what should I call you?
那麼，我該如何稱呼才好呢？
Let's see…
這個嘛…
Starting now, please call me Jinka, Miss.
就叫我壬華吧，大小姐
What?
什麼？
I think that's appropriate, based on how we're dressed.
從打扮看來，我覺得這樣稱呼才妥當
He's right.
也是
It belongs to Ms. Suiren's daughter.
這是水蓮大人女兒的衣服
The fabric and design are high quality, and it's not too old-fashioned.
不論是材質或設計都相當精緻 也沒有過時的感覺
Based on my clothes, I could look like a rich girl with a servant.
只看打扮的話 說是好人家的大小姐也不奇怪
Why is he enjoying himself that much?
他為什麼那麼開心啊？
Here is the map. For Xiaomao…
這是地圖，小貓你…
You can entrust me with Miss, sir!
請放心把大小姐交給我吧
Thank you.
麻煩你了
Sir Jinka, then.
那麼，壬華大人
-Jinka. -Yes, Miss!
-壬華 -在，大小姐
-Your posture is too straight.
-姿勢太優雅了 -是
Jinka, huh?
壬華啊
It's not so strange for a fake name,
雖然並不是太奇怪的假名
but adding the character for "Hana" is an odd choice.
但特地選了“華”這個字 真不知道該說什麼
Same with the name Jinshi,
壬氏這個名字也是
but it's not a common male name.
都不是男人姓名常用的字
Maybe we should've dressed him as a woman…
看來還是該讓他扮女裝的
No, for the peace of this world, we should avoid that.
不，為了世間和平 唯有這個還是避免才好
Where are we heading?
目的地是？
A diner right by the entrance of the pleasure district.
煙花巷前的一個飯館
I'm meeting an acquaintance there.
那裡有個認識的人正在等我
Why do I have to be a bodyguard?
為什麼要我當護衛啊？
And why do I have to keep a distance?
還要我躲著他們，到底是…
A servant stepping in front of their master? He still has lots to learn.
哪有走在主人前面的隨從啊？ 他還有得學呢
Jinka.
壬華
I'm so sorry, Miss.
十分抱歉，大小姐
Very good.
很好
It's too early for leafy vegetables, I see.
季節的關係，葉類蔬菜還很少呢
I got my allowance, so maybe
正好拿到了些零用錢
I'll have them butcher some chicken for some stew.
請肉販殺隻雞，回去一起燉著吃好了
You're shopping?
要買東西嗎？
With those clothes?
穿著那身衣服？
I wanted to get some for Old Man.
本來想給老爹嘗嘗的
He's by far the most talented
老爹不論作為醫師或藥師
doctor and apothecary in the area, but for some reason,
都是無人能出其右的英才
he has no idea how to calculate his profits and losses.
但不知道是哪裡搞錯 偏偏就是不會計算利益得失
Because of that,
因為如此
even though his profession is very profitable,
明明做著一份不會餓肚子的工作
he lives in a ramshackle hut.
卻住在那樣的破房子裡
If he ever starves,
要是真的快餓死時
I'm sure Grams would at least pour food in his mouth, but…
老鴇應該還是會餵他飯吧
-What is it? -Why aren't you talking?
-怎麼了？ -你為何都不說話？
Because there's nothing to say?
因為沒什麼話好說的？
Did I say something to offend him?
我說了什麼傷人的話嗎？
Oh, this smell is…
這個味道…
Grilled chicken skewers!
烤雞肉串！
Please wait a minute.
請等我一下
-Mister, two skewers, please! -Coming up!
-老闆，兩串燒烤 -來了
Here you are. Let's eat before it gets cold.
請用，趁還沒冷掉快吃吧
Yeah.
好
The savory chicken skin, the grease that spreads in your mouth!
香脆的雞皮，在口中化開的油脂
I can't eat this in the court.
這在宮裡可吃不到啊
You're not eating this? It's not poisoned, as you can see.
您不吃嗎？如您所見，這沒有毒喔
-Well… -Oh.
-不… -對喔
Here you are.
請用這個吧
How is it?
如何？
It's better than what I ate on the campsite. It's nice and salty.
比野營時吃的美味，鹽放得恰到好處
Campsite?
野營？
I thought eunuchs didn't do jobs that soldiers do.
我以為宦官一般 不會做那類武官的差事
Looks like he's enjoying it.
他看起來吃得津津有味就是了
Welcome back, Gaoshun.
高順，歡迎回來
Don't touch the wicker.
別碰那些編籠喔
I just applied some persimmon juice.
我剛塗上柿油而已
It's Young Master's toys.
這是少爺的玩具
-Nostalgic, right? -Yes.
-很懷念吧？ -是啊
So, how was it?
所以，怎麼樣了？
He was in a great mood.
他心情非常好
It was a great idea. Didn't expect that from you.
真不像是你會提出的好主意
Once he found a toy he liked,
少爺要是有了喜歡的玩具
Young Master would only play with that.
就只會玩那個玩具而已
If we hid the toy, he'd cry so much no one could handle him.
要是悄悄藏起來 還會哭得讓所有人束手無策
You tried to deal with him often by bringing new toys.
你為了找新的玩具給他 每次都費了很大一番功夫呢
Growing an attachment to one thing.
執著於一件事物
Sir Jinshi is not in the position to be able to do that.
壬氏大人的立場是不能如此的
You don't need to hurry so much.
你不用走得這麼急啊
You're meeting someone, right?
不是有人在等您嗎？
You should get there as fast as you can.
早點過去不是比較好嗎？
It sounds like you're impatient to get rid of me.
你這口氣，是想早點和我分開吧？
Does it?
有嗎？
It's true that I'm planning on going back to buy radishes and chicken after this.
的確，我是想趕緊分開 然後回頭買剛剛的蘿蔔和雞肉的
You know,
我說
life at the court isn't bad, is it?
宮廷的生活也不差吧？
I'm sure it's better than life in the pleasure district.
我覺得比煙花巷的生活好多了
You're right. It's not bad.
確實是不差
I serve the court of my own will.
我是自願任官的
And the room I have is clean and beautiful.
分配到的房間也很整潔
I'm just worried for my adoptive father.
但我還是擔心獨自一人的養父
I'm worried about how he's living.
有沒有好好過日子
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
I'm surprised you care about something other than medicine or poison.
沒有，只是沒想到 你也會在意藥物或毒物以外的事情
My father is my mentor in medicine.
養父是我的藥學師父
I need him to live a long life.
我希望他能活久一點 否則會很困擾的
Your father must be a talented apothecary.
看來你的養父是很厲害的藥師呢
He's skilled not only in Chinese medicine,
因為他不光是中醫，西醫也頗有心得
but Western medical practices as well.
聽說他年輕時
He used to study abroad in the West.
曾在西方留學了一段時間
He must've been extremely skilled.
這不是非常優秀嗎？
You can only study abroad if you've been selected by the country.
若沒透過國家選拔，是無法留學的
Yes, he's an accomplished person.
沒錯，他是了不起的人物
They say God doesn't grant humans two talents,
俗話說人無完人
but that's what he has.
但也有人身懷多種才華
He must be a great man.
那可真是不得了啊
Why is such a person working as an apothecary in the pleasure district?
這樣的人物 怎麼會在煙花巷當藥師？
He was granted many things, but not luck.
大概是因為他獨缺運氣吧
He has two talents,
即使他才高八斗
but his one important body part was taken away.
但重要的一斗卻被拿掉了
You're saying your adoptive father is a eunuch?
你的意思是，你的養父是宦官？
Yes, that's right.
是這樣沒錯
Did my pleasure district-style joke not land?
我的煙花巷式笑話又失敗了嗎？
Because Old Man studied abroad in the West,
似乎是因為老爹在西方留學過
he was turned into a eunuch by the previous Emperor's mother,
先帝的母親，也就是前代皇太后
or the former Empress.
以此命他成為宦官
A eunuch, apothecary, court physician…
宦官、藥師、醫官…
Have I not told him?
我沒說過嗎？
Oh, is that it?
是那棟吧？
A hotel on the second floor, a diner on the first.
樓上是客棧，樓下則是飯館
Stop by!
過來嘛
Hey, now.
喂，真是的
Oh, I see.
啊，原來如此
That's why he came here disguised.
特地喬裝的理由我明白了
You should have come to the pleasure district, then.
既然如此 來逛個煙花巷不是很好嗎？
-Huh? What do you mean? -It's nothing.
-嗯？什麼意思？ -沒什麼
Apothecary, are you familiar with the Verdigris House's regulars?
藥師，你和綠青館的常客熟嗎？
Yes, if they're the flashy type.
嗯，若是行事張揚的客人…
What kind of men?
是些怎麼樣的客人？
It's a secret. A brothel is confidential.
這是祕密，我有保密義務
In that case,
那麼…
how do you lower the value of a courtesan?
若是想降低娼妓身價的話 該怎麼做？
That's a very unpleasant question.
聽到了讓人不快的話呢
There are many ways, especially for high-class courtesans.
方法有很多，特別是高級娼妓
At the Verdigris House,
在綠青館
most courtesans are trained when they are apprentices.
娼妓在見習娼妓小丫頭時期 就會接受全套的教育
Out of those, they're divided between the beautiful and plain girls,
其中會分為面貌姣好者，和其餘之人
and the latter will take clients and sell themselves after their debut.
後者在初次露面後 便會立刻開始接客賣身
Girls with potential will serve tea and find clients
另一方面，有前途者會從奉茶開始
through manners and education.
以教養來招攬客人
Their value will keep going up,
身價也會慢慢提高
and if she stops coming out as much at that point,
抬高身價後，便會開始減少露面次數
then you have a popular courtesan who will cost a year's worth of silver to have tea.
光是奉茶就要散盡一年銀兩的 紅牌娼妓，就是如此造就的
Some of these girls remain untouched by clients until they're bought out.
贖身之前 從未被客人碰過的娼妓，也是有的
They're valuable because they're untainted flowers.
沒人碰過的花朵才有價值
If she is touched, her value would go down by half. Finally,
一旦摘下，身價就會減半 更進一步說…
if she becomes pregnant, she is practically worthless.
若是讓她懷孕，就更是毫無身價可言
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集預告）
Next Episode, "Lakan."
下一集，《羅漢》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻譯：楊易